Guide to Mount Vernon Seminary and College Spring Valley Campus and Florence Foerderer scrapbook collection, 1925-1957 MVC0004.MS
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Mount Vernon Seminary and College Spring Valley Campus and Florence Foerderer scrapbook collection
1925-1957
1943-1950
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MVC0004.MS
1.5 Linear Feet
This collection contains newspaper articles, photographs, songs, and correspondence related to the Spring Valley campus of the Mount Vernon Seminary and College and the student life of student Florence Foerderer. The bulk of the material dates from 1943 to 1950.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Biography of Florence Foerderer
Florence Foerderer (1926-1999) grew up in Bryn Mawr, Pennsylvania. She graduated from the Mount Vernon Junior College in 1948. During her time at Mount Vernon, Florence served as senior class president. Upon graduation she worked for a time at the College. In 1949, Florence attended the Summer School for American Students of the University of Oslo, Norway. Based on the limited data in this collection she appeared to work for Mount Vernon in some capacity although the record of this is scant and there is no data about what she may have done or the duration. Florence never married and later in life became a successful dog breeder.
Historical note about Mount Vernon
On December 28, 1942 The Mount Vernon Seminary and Junior College moved from its Nebraska Avenue location to the Spring Valley neighborhood. This move was precipiated by the United States Navy decision to take the buildings and grounds of the Mount Vernon Seminary for World War II initiatives. Mount Vernon received zoning approval to use a portion of the Garfinkel's Department Store at 4340 Fordham Road for classrooms, a study hall, library and assembly hall. This formed the main part of the school with eight houses in the Spring Valley neighborhood serving as faculty and student residences and several other buildings housing other essential offices such as an infirmary and classroom spaces. The students used American University's athletic facilities for most of the physical exercise classes. The Spring Valley houses were temporary quarters until 1946.
In late 1943, a jury awarded the school more than one million dollars as compensation for the loss of the Nebraska Avenue property. This award allowed the school to pay off its remaining debt, but the Trustees knew that finding a new permanent campus was essential to the continued existence of the school. The Trustees began looking in early 1944 and soon after purchased property at Foxhall Road, the site of the current Mount Vernon Campus.
In 1999, George Washington University acquired the Mount Vernon College.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Collection acquired by GWU upon merger with Mount Vernon College. Collection transferred to Foggy Bottom campus in 2009.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains newspaper articles, photographs, songs, and correspondence related to the Spring Valley campus and the student life of Florence Foerderer including a trip Ms. Foerderer took to Oslo Norway as an exchange student. The photographs show both the exterior views of many of the Spring Valley houses used by students for classrooms and dormitories and also interior views of students studying and attending classes such as painting. The scrapbooks are a mix of data about her time at Mount Vernon including exams, Mount Vernon policies, and letters from classmates and teachers, images of student life, some material about her time in Washington, D.C., and brochures and letters related to her studies in Norway. This inclusive dates of the material is 1925-1957, but the bulk of the material dates from 1943-1950.
Arrangement
Arranged in a loose chronological order. The order within each scrapbook was maintained which was not always a true chronology.
Other Finding Aids
The Foerderer family papers reside at The Historical Society of Pennsylvania. These records pertain primarily to the work and life of Florence Foerderer's parents, Percival E. Foerderer and Ethel Brown Foerderer.
http://www.hsp.org/files/findingaid3102foerderer.pdf
Women -- Education; Women's colleges; Mount Vernon College; Mount Vernon Seminary
- Florence Foerderer's scrapbook, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Florence Foerderer's scrapbook, circa 1935 - circa 1948 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Florence Foerderer's scrapbook, circa 1935 - circa 1948 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Florence Foerderer's scrapbook, circa 1935 - circa 1948 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Florence Foerderer's scrapbook, circa 1935 - circa 1948 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  General
  This folder contains the Mount Vernon Junior College handbook.
- Florence Foerderer photograph album, 1943-1950, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Most of these images are not dated or identified. There are images from a ski trip titled Sky Top 1948. There are also images from a May 11, 1948 boat trip Florence, as Senior Class President of the Junior College, took with George W Lloyd, President of Mount Vernon College and Mrs. Olwen Lloyd, Headmistress of the Mount Vernon Seminary and other students on the "Sea Cloud" boat owned by Joseph E. Davies.
- Spring Valley newspaper clippings, circa 1943 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Spring Valley MVS clippings since the move to Fordham Road scrapbook, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Scrapbook [1/2], 1946-1953 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Scrapbook [2/2], 1948-1952 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Spring Valley correspondence, programs, historical records, 1942-1957 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Programs - songs and Chapel, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Photos of MVS and students, circa 1940s (Box 3, Folder 3)
- The Clearing House student newspaper, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Florence Foerderer Oslo travel scrapbook [1/2], 1950 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Florence Foerderer Oslo travel scrapbook [2/2], 1950 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Images of Mount Vernon students especially Florence Foerderer, Circa 1948 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  The images include theater performances and other student related scenes. There are numerous images of Florence Foerderer. According to the donor these images are from the files of Florence Foederer. The images appear to have once been part of a scrapbook.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Gift of Ethel Davis, June 17, 2014 (2014.019)